Hey everyone, it's Richard, you watching
The Plain Bagel. A couple of weeks ago,
amid Canada's spring economic update,
Canadians were surprised with some
interesting news. When Prime Minister
Mark Carney announced that we would be
getting a sovereign wealth fund, the
so-called Canada Strong Fund, a pool of
government money that would be investing
in major Canadian infrastructure
projects. Part of the government's big
push to spur so-called nation-building
projects for the country. Now, Canadians
are no stranger to funds. We already
have the First and Last Mile Fund,
Canada Housing Infrastructure Fund,
Build Community Strong Fund, Canada
Public Transit Fund. Launching new funds
is basically the government's favorite
pastime. And many of these funds are
already aimed at investing in Canadian
infrastructure. But this would be the
country's first national sovereign
wealth fund, which compared to the other
funds, which are more or less just
vehicles for government spending, would
be designed primarily to make money for
the government. The goal of sovereign
wealth funds is typically to make
profitable investments to preserve and
grow the pool of money to benefit the
government for generations to come, much
like how you or I might invest our
savings for retirement. And they've been
a tremendous benefit to some other
countries who have them. Mark Carney in
his speech, for example, highlighted
Norway, which has the largest sovereign
wealth fund worth over two trillion US
dollars, and has been able to cover up
to 25%
of its government's annual spending with
proceeds from the fund. But what's
particularly unique about Canada's
proposal is the plan to let Canadians
participate.
>> We'll make it easy for you to invest in
the fund to help build Canada strong for
all.
>> Now, while some are excited about the
opportunity to both invest in and
benefit from their own economy, and
others are just relieved that the Prime
Minister is announcing a retail
investment opportunity that isn't a meme
coin rug pull, the announcement has been
met with a fair amount of skepticism.
After all, the Canadian government
doesn't have the best track record when
it comes to infrastructure investment
decisions, and typically sovereign
wealth funds require
sovereign wealth or in effect a budget
surplus, something Canada doesn't have,
which has led to a lot of criticism that
Canada will effectively be borrowing
money to start this fund.
>> He's talking about a sovereign
debt fund.
>> So today we'll dive into how a sovereign
fund would work,
why Canada would want one, the
challenges the country will likely run
into, and things Canadians should
consider if they decide they want to
invest in this fund.
>> Especially given that Carney has floated
the idea of guaranteeing investor
capital.
>> We intend to provide it in a way where
the investment itself, the actual amount
of money is protected. It's something
consistent to buying a government bond.
>> So, what are the details we do have
about the Canada Strong Fund? Uh well,
it's still very early, but as
highlighted by the government's own
announcement, the sovereign wealth fund
will be kickstarted with $25 billion
from the government, contributed over 3
years, and will invest in everything
from infrastructure and advanced
manufacturing to energy and mining. The
investing will be equity-based, meaning
the fund will look to own a portion of
the projects and share in the profits,
rather than just lending money like some
other Canadian programs, and it will
look to help fund private projects. So,
the government themselves isn't planning
on taking on and developing these
projects. With Carney highlighting the
example of the Canada Pacific Railway,
which was built privately, but continues
to be a major piece of Canadian
infrastructure today. Now, in terms of
who will manage this fund, the
government plans to set up a new
arms-length Crown Corporation that will
employ an independent CEO and board
members to try and foster independent
and professional management. Now,
despite the comparison to Norway's
sovereign wealth fund, the two aren't
really all that comparable when it comes
to scale. At $25 billion over 3 years,
the fund makes up just about 1.4% of the
government's annual spending, and the
total fund size amounts to less than 1%
of the country's GDP. Whereas Norway's
sovereign wealth fund is massive at over
four times the country's annual output.
However, the goal of the fund is to help
bolster other investments in these
infrastructure projects as well. Again,
there's that retail component where
Canadians can invest alongside the
government in these projects, and the
goal is also to attract capital from
private investors like Blackstone and
other institutional investors who would
typically back these major
infrastructure projects. So, at a
surface level, you can see the appeal,
especially given that Canada is in need
of the investment dollars. Canada has
long struggled with stagnant
productivity that many attribute to a
lack of investment with business
investment per Canadian worker having
actually declined from 2014 to 2025. And
Canada ranking last among the G7 nations
in terms of machinery, equipment, and
intellectual property investment. And
many view the country as being ripe with
potential for natural resource
development. Uh historically, projects
have been held up primarily by
burdensome regulation and roadblocks
imposed over environmental concerns. But
the country hosts the fourth largest oil
reserve globally, is abundant with
agricultural real estate, is a top
producer of key metals and minerals such
as potash and uranium, and is estimated
to have some of the most valuable
natural resource reserves in the world.
And Mark Carney has signaled an intent
to pivot from the previous leadership's
aversion to natural resource
development. It's all also very much on
brand for Mark Carney. Prior to being
Prime Minister, Mark Carney was actually
chairman for the board of directors of
Brookfield Asset Management, a company
whose main function is raising investor
capital for and managing private
investments such as infrastructure. And
so, for some Canadians, it seems like a
no-brainer. We have the right guy for
the job, and with Canadians themselves
able to invest in the upside of their
economy's turnaround while seemingly set
to benefit from government protections,
it seems like a win-win. With Mark
Carney also highlighting in his
announcement,
>> Many countries that are blessed with
natural resources like Norway have
sovereign wealth funds.
>> Nonetheless, as mentioned, the plan has
been met with a good amount of
skepticism. Uh with one of the biggest
criticisms being that
Canada doesn't exactly have money for a
sovereign wealth fund. As you see, while
it's true that most sovereign wealth
funds have been funded by countries who
have abundant natural resources like
Canada, namely oil and gas, unlike
Canada, most of these countries have
actually nationalized their oil and gas
production. In fact, all five of the
largest oil-based sovereign wealth funds
in the world all come from countries
with government-owned oil production,
including Norway itself, which is how
many of these funds got their money in
the first place. Many of these countries
found that they were making more money
than they spent each year from their
natural resource development, and so
they saved and invested the excess for
their future benefit via sovereign
wealth funds. But Canada's oil
production is predominantly private,
meaning that most of the proceeds go to
the owners of the companies running
these operations. Uh yes, the government
does benefit from the tax dollars,
carbon pricing, and regulatory levies
charged to these operations, but it
doesn't see the same benefit as
countries like Norway who capture the
entire bottom line. Even the oil and gas
royalties charged for the right to use
this government land goes primarily to
the provincial governments, namely
Alberta, who in fact does have a
sub-sovereign wealth fund, the Alberta
Heritage Savings Trust Fund, which
currently sits around 32 billion
Canadian dollars and was funded by
resource royalties. By the federal
level, Canada pretty consistently spends
more money than it makes, with it last
seeing a tiny fiscal surplus in 2015.
With the country's gross debt to GDP
already over 100% and growing, many are
nervous about the idea of borrowing more
money to set up this fund. Now, just
because a country has budget deficits
doesn't mean it can't have a sovereign
wealth fund. Uh China itself runs one of
the largest sovereign wealth funds right
after Norway, despite itself running a
budget deficit, and a number of other
deficit countries, including the UK,
have themselves announced or considered
putting together similar funds. Heck,
just over a year ago Trump himself
signed an executive order instructing
the government to explore its own
sovereign wealth fund. Which doesn't
help Carney's reputation of stealing
ideas from conservatives, but regardless
you get the point, right? It is feasible
to have a sovereign wealth fund even if
your government spends more money than
it makes. Much like how households might
invest despite themselves having a
mortgage, it can still make sense if you
have a low enough cost of capital. And
with Canada's current 10-year treasury
yield sitting at 3.5% and the 10-year
average return for sovereign wealth
funds sitting at 6.3% the plan could be
fiscally sustainable. But that doesn't
leave much room for error. Which brings
us to another key concern about the
fund. The investment mandate. To earn
their returns sovereign wealth funds
typically diversify their holdings to
make sure that their money is being
conservatively managed given that losing
money with a sovereign wealth fund would
be pretty politically unpopular. Uh the
average allocation is split pretty
evenly between private markets, public
equity or stocks, and fixed income. And
investments are also typically
diversified by region ensuring that the
fund can pursue opportunities globally
wherever they might exist and ensuring
that there isn't too much exposure to
any particular region. In fact, Norway's
sovereign wealth fund doesn't invest any
of its money into its own country. The
Canada Strong Fund on the other hand
plans to invest entirely in Canada
entirely in private major infrastructure
projects. Which naturally is pretty
concentrated. Now that might not matter
for other Canadian investment funds that
are more policy driven and it is quite
common with other sovereign wealth funds
for the country to use them in a way
that furthers national interests. Like
what we've seen with China and Saudi
Arabia. But if the fund's true aim is to
achieve market returns as Carney has
highlighted limiting the investment
universe to Canadian infrastructure
projects could make that difficult to
achieve. Which of course matters when
we're having Canadians themselves tying
their wealth to the funds performance.
Now again, Carney has floated the idea
of protecting investor capital,
seemingly suggesting that retail
investors would only see potential
upside. But that just expands the risk
faced by the government if the projects
don't perform, which for retail
investors could also just translate into
higher taxes later down the line. And
then there's a concern around execution
risk, given Canada's track record of
cost overruns with its previous major
infrastructure projects. In 2018, the
federal government, for example,
purchased the Trans Mountain pipeline
for $4.5 billion from Kinder Morgan to
save an expansion project from being
canceled. And while the project was
completed in 2024 and helped bring oil
to Canada's West Coast, it wasn't,
strictly speaking, profitable, with the
project costing roughly $34 billion,
over six times the original estimated
amount. And then there are the
underlying factors that have contributed
to this lack of investment in the first
place. The extensive regulatory approval
processes, the regulatory and political
misalignment of the provinces
themselves, who also have meaningful
sway over how these projects fare. Even
the moderate to high risk of corruption
and organized criminal activity with
Canada's commercial construction sector.
Not to mention, the federal government
has already tried its hand at
infrastructure co-investment. In 2017,
the Trudeau government announced the
Canada Infrastructure Bank, which itself
sought to catalyze private investment in
Canadian infrastructure with mixed
success. In 2022, the House of Commons
Standing Committee on Transportation,
Infrastructure, and Communities actually
recommended the bank be abolished for
failing to meet expectations, though it
has since become more active. And this
has been one of the biggest pushbacks to
all of this. Canada's government has
already been extensively involved in the
country's economy through Crown
corporations like Export Development
Canada, Business Development Canada, and
of course the Canada Infrastructure
Bank. None of which have seemingly
solved the country's investment issues.
So with some believing the solution to
Canada's woes is less government
intervention, not more, starting yet
another Crown corporation doesn't stir a
lot of enthusiasm for certain crowds.
With opposition leader Pierre Poilievre
highlighting, "If a project has a
business case,
why would the government need to fund
it?
If it doesn't have a business case,
why would the government want to fund
it?" Which brings us to the ultimate
question,
is this a good idea?
Well, there's a great piece in the Globe
and Mail that highlights a
three-question framework for assessing
the sovereign wealth fund. Is it
necessary? Can it stay independent from
politics? And does the fiscal math make
sense? To the first again, Canada does
need to foster more investment in its
infrastructure, especially in the face
of frayed relations with the US. And
government investment may help to
de-risk some of these projects for other
investment groups, given that the
government will naturally be motivated
to ensure they aren't held up
unnecessarily. And while the retail
aspect is a risky one, it could also
prove beneficial. We've seen a wave of
Canadians pulling back on US travel and
spending amid the heightened tensions,
but investment dollars have still
primarily flowed south of the border.
So, with the current sentiment, the
opportunity to invest in strengthening
the country's economy
could prove quite popular. Now, to the
second question, independence will
depend a lot on how the fund is
structured. Uh the $32 billion Alberta
Heritage Savings Trust Fund has itself
been tapped regularly by the provincial
government, which has impacted its
growth. The fund's balance was
effectively flat over the decade between
2007 and 2017, despite the fund
achieving a 10-year return of 7.7%.
And some have raised concerns over Mark
Carney's own conflicts of interest.
While the Prime Minister's investments
are currently held in a blind trust,
meaning he can't legally influence how
the money's invested, his work with
Brookfield left him with millions of
dollars of stock options for the company
prior to him transferring the assets.
But Carney claims that the fund will be
managed at arm's length, meaning that
investment decisions will be made based
on investment rationale rather than
political motivations. And if the
government is able to replicate Norway
in this sense, which mind you is a bit
of an outlier in the world of sovereign
wealth funds, that would certainly be
beneficial. Part of the reason sovereign
wealth funds have actually
underperformed a standard 60/40
portfolio is because of that focus at
times on political aims or national
interest. The projects these funds
sometimes pursue for those reasons
aren't always profitable. Finally, does
the fiscal math make sense? Technically,
the fund will be a good idea if it earns
a return above the country's cost of
capital, which should be doable given
that treasury yields are again fairly
low. But profitable infrastructure
projects will largely depend on the
government's ability to deliver on its
other campaign promises. One of the
biggest hurdles for infrastructure
investments in Canada is the lengthy
regulatory approval process, which can
hold up capital, make investment
opportunities less attractive, and
thereby discourage investment in the
country. So, you can't really assess the
fund itself without assessing the other
actions that the government will take to
streamline infrastructure project
development both at the federal and
importantly the provincial level. Now,
to that point, the Prime Minister has
introduced the Major Projects Office,
which aims to fast-track nation-building
projects with the single point of
contact for approvals and a maximum
two-year review process. And it looks
like the plan is for the Canada Strong
Fund to actually work in collaboration
with the Major Projects Office to help
source investment ideas, which could
also help expedite the construction
process. But the downside risk is still
very real, and if the government is
going to protect retail investors from
any losses, that will just amount to a
double whammy for the government if
projects fail to meet expectations,
which adds more pressure on Carney to
deliver on the streamlining
infrastructure promises. But given how
long these projects can take to develop,
we'll have to wait and see how
successful these initiatives prove. Now,
in terms of whether Canadians should
invest in this fund for reasons beyond
just wanting to support their economy,
we just again don't have enough
information given that there's not even
a formal mandate about how the fund will
be invested, but there are a couple of
considerations to keep in mind if you're
someone considering the idea. With the
key one being liquidity. As a private
investment fund looking to invest in
Canadian infrastructure projects, it's
very likely that the Canada Strong Fund
will be an illiquid investment, meaning
that it might be difficult to pull your
money out of once you've invested in it.
There might be a minimum holding period
or potentially a cap on what percentage
of money can be pulled out of the fund
by Canadians. Reason being that major
infrastructure projects aren't very easy
to sell out of. These aren't like stocks
or ETFs where you can find a buyer
within seconds. These projects can take
over a decade to turn a profit. And
trying to sell infrastructure projects
to monetize something beforehand can
itself take years of negotiations. So,
likely take some time before the fund
and as a result its investors are able
to monetize their investments. Now, this
is a risk that many institutional
investors are much accustomed to, which
is why it's common to see things like
sovereign wealth funds holding a good
chunk of their money in private equity
and the like. But, it's not always
appropriate at the retail level. In
fact, in the US, we've recently seen
some turmoil with private market retail
funds with withdrawals being gated for a
number of large private credit funds as
a wave of investors all tried to pull
their money out at once. It's also worth
considering concentration risk. Many
Canadians already have a home bias with
their investments whereby they hold a
larger relative amount of their money in
Canadian stocks versus say a
well-diversified international
portfolio. And actually, a lot of our
economic future is already determined by
the Canadian economy. So, there can be
some benefit to diversifying investments
beyond the borders of your home country.
That being said, there could very well
be some low-hanging fruit return
opportunities within the country. And if
the government guarantees retail
investor capital, like with Canadian
bonds, then actually removes a lot of
the risk and makes it much more
attractive. Disregarding the
higher-level government implications.
Though, the details there still need to
be confirmed. And the government may yet
offer some tax incentives that would
make it more attractive similar to say
the TFSA or RRSP where there would be
tax deferral or tax exempt status for
this fund. And of course some people are
going to want to invest for reasons
beyond the financial implications. So
that's also worth considering as well.
But ultimately it's very early so we're
kind of assessing the whole thing fairly
blind. So we'll have to wait and see
ultimately how things develop. Thanks
for joining me today. I hope you found
this video helpful. If you did please do
make sure to like subscribe all that
good stuff. It does help the channel
tremendously. And let me know your
thoughts on the Canada Strong Fund in
the comments down below. Thanks again
for joining me and as always
be safe out there.